Finding aid to the Florence Cross Kitchelt papers SSC.MS.00086
Sophia Smith Collection
Florence Cross Kitchelt papers
1900-1959
Sophia Smith Collection
Kitchelt, Florence Ledyard Cross, 1874-1961
SSC.MS.00086
.75 linear feet (2 containers)
Florence Cross Kitchelt was a settlement house worker and social worker. Kitchelt's journals describe settlement work in New York and New Haven, CT. Correspondence includes descriptive letters to her parents; letters from settlement friends; letters from Sadie Rubin, an inmate at the New York State Reformatory for Women; and from members of the Laureate Literary Society, which Kitchelt founded and directed. Other materials include autobiographical pieces, articles, verses, and notes.
Biographical / Historical
Florence Ledyard Cross Kitchelt was born in Rochester, New York, on 17 December 1874. She graduated from Wells College in 1897. For two years after college, she worked at the George Junior Republic, a self-governing community for troubled youth. From 1900-04, she worked at the New York College Settlement at 95 Rivington Street in Manhattan's Lower East Side and its summer location in Mt. Ivy, New York. In 1904, she returned to reform work as a volunteer probation officer for women with New York City's Essex Market Court. From 1904 to 1905, she worked at the Lowell House settlement in New Haven, Connecticut. She was the head worker in the Little Italy House in Brooklyn (1903) and another Italian American settlement, the "Housekeeping Center," in Rochester (1907-10). She married Richard Kitchelt in 1911. After her marriage, she was active in several civic and political causes. She volunteered and wrote articles for suffrage, trade union, socialist, and pacifist organizations in New York and Connecticut. She died in Wilberforce, Ohio on 4 April 1961.
Scope and Contents
The Florence Cross Kitchelt papers consist of diaries, writings, printed material, correspondence, memorabilia, and photographs. Most material is from 1900 to 1904 and covers Kitchelt's years at the College Settlement and Lowell House.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into three series:
I. Writings
II. Correspondence
III. Subjects
Related Material
Additional papers of Florence Kitchelt are at Yale University; the Schlesinger Library, Harvard University; and the Kroch Library, Cornell University. There are also journals (1905-1947) available on microfilm in Neilson Library, Smith College.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Florence Kitchelt donated her papers concerning settlement house work to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1959. After her death in 1961, her sister, Dorothy Cross Zeiger, donated some biographical items and articles.
Literature--Societies, etc.--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Social settlements--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Social settlements--Connecticut--New Haven--History--Sources; Social work with immigrants--United States--History--Sources; Women social reformers--United States--History--Sources; diaries; correspondence; memorabilia; photographs; clippings; Kitchelt, Florence Ledyard Cross, 1874-1961; unknown; Kitchelt, Florence; Kitchelt, Florence Cross
- SERIES I. WRITINGS
  - Autobiographical typescripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - College settlement journals
    - 95 Rivington St., New York, Jun-Jul 1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Summer House, Mount Ivy, NY, Aug-Sep 1900 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 95 Rivington St., Sep 1900-Aug 1904 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
    - Lowell House, New Haven CT, Oct 1904-Feb 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notes on the journals, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Address to the "King's Daughters,", 1902 [1904?] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "A Chapter in the History of Human Rights," Journal of Human Relations, [re: Susan B. Anthony], Winter 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Verses, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Who" and "They Have Contributed": typescripts re: "Negroes" and segregation, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Outgoing to mother and sister, 1901; 1904 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Incoming
    - Bonime, Ellis, 1902-03 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Braun, Jacob, 1902-03 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bromberg, Abraham, 1901; 1903 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Burstein, Sam, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cohen, Nathan, 1902-05 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Halperin, Jacob, 1902; 1904 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Markham, Edwin, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Rubin, Sadie, 1902-03 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Wolf, Irving, 1902-03 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- SERIES III. SUBJECTS
  - College settlements: photographs of settlement houses (including 95 Rivington Street) and residents, clippings, and memorabilia, 1902-06; undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Laureate Literary Society: memorabilia, 1901; 1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)